Guide to the Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden papers
1836-1967
1887-1967
YCAL MSS 706
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.42
(4 boxes)
The Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden Papers consist of diaries, photographs, a scrapbook, correspondence, clippings, playbills, a portrait painting of Louden, and other printed material, regarding the personal and professional life of American actress Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden.
Valentine, Elizabeth H. (Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden), 1877-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bradford S. Lamb, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Oversize box 3 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden (1877-1971)
Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden, American actress. Louden was born in Brooklyn on March 16, 1877, attended Cornell University, married Irishman Thomas Louden in 1911. She was active in the suffrage movement during the 1910s, while still appearing on stage regularly, often in Shakespearean roles. She had small parts in film roles between 1939 and 1965. She died on July 23, 1971 in Westerly, Rhode Island.
Scope and Contents
The Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden Papers consist of diaries, photographs, a scrapbook, correspondence, clippings, playbills, a framed portrait painting, and other printed material, regarding the personal and professional life of American actress Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Diaries, 1932, 1950-1955. II. Photographs, 1887-circa 1965. III. Other Papers, 1912-1962. IV. Printed Material, 1836, 1897-1967.
Actresses -- United States; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States; Theater -- United States; Diaries; Oil paintings (visual works); Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Playbills; Theater programs; Actresses -- United States -- 20th Century; Valentine, Elizabeth H. (Elizabeth Hacker Valentine Louden)
- Photographs, 1887-circa 1965; Series II; 15
  - Photographs of Louden, her family, theater productions, and snapshots of travel, 1887-circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7-16)
  - Photographs of Louden and theater productions, undated
  - Photograph case, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook of photographs, clippings, and a program, 1900-1908 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains photographs portraying theater productions, clippings of theater reviews, and a program for The Rose and the Ring by the Sage Dramatic Club
- Diaries, 1932, 1950-1955; Series I; 6
  Contains personal diaries kept by Louden.
  - Six diaries, 1932, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
- Other Papers, 1912-1962, undated; Series III; 4
  Contains correspondence between Louden and various individuals. Included among the correspondence are photographs and printed material. Also included are two writings on Germany by Garrett Stearly and Nan Stearly.
  - "Professional correspondence, Elizabeth Valentine", 1912-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Contains correspondence with various individuals and printed material regarding Louden's acting career
  - Correspondence with various individuals, 1926-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes photographs and printed material
  - "Confidential Report from Germany" by Garrett Stearly, typescript; and "Notes on Germany: The New Year 1949" by Nan Stearly, typescript carbon, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Painted portrait of Louden, framed, undated
- Printed Material, 1836, 1897-1967, undated; Series IV; 10
  Contains clippings, playbills, and an issue of the magazine Promenade, relating to Louden's acting career. The books belonged to Louden and often contain inscriptions of ownership. Also included is an empty leather book holder.
  - Clippings, 1914-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Playbills, 1900-1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1911, undated
  - Science and Health with Key to the Scriptures (The Christian Science Publishing Society), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The Plays of Shakespeare (Doubleday and McClure Co., 1897) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Quotations from the British Poets: Being a Pocket Directory of Their Most Admired Passages (Charles Wells, 1836) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Temple Shakespeare, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Shakespeare's Comedy of Much Ado About Nothing (J. M. Dent), undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Promenade, 1947 January (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - One empty leather book holder, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Oversize Material
  - Photographs of Louden and theater productions, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Oversize box 3 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Clippings, 1911, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Painted portrait of Louden, framed, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Restricted fragile material.